<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Taras Kaduk</title>
    <link>/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Taras Kaduk</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 26 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>CV</title>
      <link>/page/cv/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/page/cv/</guid>
      <description>.column-left{ float: left; width: 33%; } .column-center{ display: inline-block; width: 33%; } .column-right{ float: right; width: 33%; }  Contact  phone: 904-662-9453 email: contact@taraskaduk.com location: Jacksonville, FL   Summary  Love R Love data science Love online learning, self-education, love spreading knowledge, love helping people learn stuff Hate redundancy, bad processes, manual tasks that should have been automated. Living a minimalism-driven and adventurous life, preferring flexibility and ability to move to new places or work remotely  Mad R Skills  tidyverse forecast caret rmarkdown   Other rad skills  SQL Power BI Data Visualization All things data   Languages:  Russian - native Ukrainian - native English - fluent French - elementary to intermediate    Main Work Experience Manager, Business Intelligence &amp;amp; CRM Suddath | April 2017 - Present | Jacksonville, FL</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Imposterism in Data Science: Addressing the credentials problem</title>
      <link>/post/2018-01-impostor/impostor/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2018-01-impostor/impostor/</guid>
      <description>Cross-posted: Medium 
We happen to talk a lot about the impostor syndrome these days. No wonder — it seems to be an important subject. But what is it? That feeling of faking it while others clearly know what’s they’re doing.
Many attempts have been made to clarify the issue. Explaining that it is OK, that we all feel that way going through life. Et cetera et cetera. Some advice has gone as far as making the impostor syndrome a badge of honor.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The 4 Stages of Data Analytics Maturity: Challenging the Gartner’s Model</title>
      <link>/post/2016-12-4-stages/4-stages/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 22 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2016-12-4-stages/4-stages/</guid>
      <description>Cross-posted: LinkedIn, Medium 
If you happen to work in analytics, data science or business intelligence, you’ve probably seen one of the iterations of this Gartner’s graph on stages of data analysis in a company:
 The figure above shows various stages of analytics maturity, from “descriptive” to “prescriptive”. I’ve seen it so many times, it became an eyesore to me.
There is nothing wrong with it. This look nicely breaks down the evolution of analytics into understandable parts and pairs each stage with a question to be answered: what happened, why did it happen, what will happen, how can we make it happen.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My first shiny app: calculating your hourly rate as a consultant</title>
      <link>/post/2018-01-shiny-rate/shiny_rate/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 13 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2018-01-shiny-rate/shiny_rate/</guid>
      <description>(One year after building it and forgetting it) Cross-posted: Medium
   Is it just me, or is your hard drive also full of abandoned projects, ideas et cetera? I know I’m not alone.
Cleaning up my R folder the other day, I stumbled upon a file I hardly remember creating. It is was a Shiny app built to help one calculate the hourly rate of services, given a desired income and an amount of time working (billable hours in a day, days in a week, weeks in a year).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>On Importance of Minimalism in Retrospective Analytics</title>
      <link>/post/2018-01-sass/sass/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 12 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2018-01-sass/sass/</guid>
      <description>Cross-posted: Medium, LinkedIn 
Hey, analyst, how is life? Talk to me. Do you love what you do for life, do you like all things data?
 Yet, do you sometimes feel like you’re a Sisyphus rolling a giant rock of data up the hill every day, only to see it go down with a racket in the evening (and you know what you’re going to do tomorrow)? Or, do you imagine yourself being a plate spinner at a circus, only instead of plates and poles you’ve got five dozen reports to spin, and instead of an entertained crowd you’ve got your co-workers, managers and senior executives watching your “performance” and asking to add more plates, and God forbid any one plate falls?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>When your data analysis is validated on The Late Show with Stephen Colbert</title>
      <link>/post/2017-09-mpaa/mpaa-damon/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 10 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2017-09-mpaa/mpaa-damon/</guid>
      <description>Cross-posted: Medium
About a month ago, I wrote a little article about the MPAA rating system. I set up to find out if their lettering system does any justice to the actual content seen on the screen. Briefly speaking, it does, but with caveats.
One of such caveats was the effect of profanity. What my quick and dirty data analysis showed was that profanity was the sure thing that could send a movie into an R category:</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Create World Pixel Maps in R</title>
      <link>/post/2017-11-pixel-maps/pixel-maps/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2017-11-pixel-maps/pixel-maps/</guid>
      <description>Cross-posted: Medium
Today, I’m going to show you how to make pixel maps in R. Why pixel maps? Because they look awesome!
I was searching on the web for a while, but couldn’t find a good tutorial. Being stubborn as I am, I eventually figured out a way to get what I want. You know, if you torture your code enough, it might give you what you need.
Setup First, of course, loading required packages.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Do MPAA movie ratings mean anything?</title>
      <link>/post/2017-09-mpaa/mpaa/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 30 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2017-09-mpaa/mpaa/</guid>
      <description>Cross-posted: Medium 
Intro Being a parent in modern days is lots of fun. Not only all of us are pretty much winging it, not having any idea what we’re doing (seriously, you need a license to do braids and nails, yet raising a human being a future member of society is a no-brainer, right?) — we are also constantly being watched and judged by other parents.
When it comes to watching movies with our six-year-old son, we don’t have a strict set of rules.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title></title>
      <link>/post/2018-01-shiny-rate/readme/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/2018-01-shiny-rate/readme/</guid>
      <description>This is my first R Shiny app. It helps you calculate your rate as a consiltant, taking into account many factors at the same time.
Please see full explanation at my blog post at https://taraskaduk.com/2018/01/13/shiny_rate/.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>