<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Taraas</title>
    <link>/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Taraas</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 08 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>CV</title>
      <link>/page/cv/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jan 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/page/cv/</guid>
      <description>Summary  Love R Love data science Love online learning, self-education, love spreading knowledge, love helping people learn stuff Hate redundancy, bad processes, manual tasks that should have been automated. Living a minimalism-driven and adventurous life, preferring flexibility and ability to move to new places or work remotely   .column-left{ float: left; width: 33%; } .column-center{ display: inline-block; width: 33%; } .column-right{ float: right; width: 33%; }  Mad R Skills  tidyverse forecast caret rmarkdown   Other rad skills  SQL Power BI Data Visualization All things data   Languages:  Russian - native Ukrainian - native English - fluent French - elementary to intermediate    Main Work Experience Manager, Business Intelligence &amp;amp; CRM Suddath | April 2017 - Present | Jacksonville, FL</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Create World Pixel Maps in R</title>
      <link>/2017/11/26/pixel-maps/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 26 Nov 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/11/26/pixel-maps/</guid>
      <description>Today, I’m going to show you how to make pixel maps in R. Why pixel maps? Because they look awesome!
I was searching on the web for a while, but couldn’t find a good tutorial. Being stubborn as I am, I eventually figured out a way to get what I want. You know, if you torture your code enough, it might give you what you need.
Setup First, of course, loading required packages.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Do MPAA movie ratings mean anything?</title>
      <link>/2017/09/30/mpaa/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 30 Sep 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2017/09/30/mpaa/</guid>
      <description>Intro Being a parent in modern days is lots of fun. Not only all of us are pretty much winging it, not having any idea what we’re doing (seriously, you need a license to do braids and nails, yet raising a human being a future member of society is a no-brainer, right?) — we are also constantly being watched and judged by other parents.
When it comes to watching movies with our six-year-old son, we don’t have a strict set of rules.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>